Register of the Herbert Hoover subject collection, 1895-2006
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1897-1964 (Box 149-218)
  - Speeches, articles, and memoranda. See also CLIPPINGS, box 230. (Box 149)
    - Acceptance speech for receiving an honorary doctor of law degree from the University of the State of New York, Albany, (degree conferred in absentia, speech not delivered)., April 25, 1958
    - Tribute to women, (speech not delivered)., June 22, 1958
    - "Thank you, Miss Gray!" Reader's Digest, July 1959.
    - Speech material for the presidential campaign (not used)., 1960
    - Address at dedication of Hoover Dike at Lake Okeechobee, Fla., January 12, 1961.
    - "The Inheritance of the Next Generation," Independence Hall, Philadelphia, June 27, 1961.
    - "Christmas Message,", December 25, 1961.
    - Christmas message, (unpublished)., 1961
    - Address before the Key Largo Anglers Club, April 1962.
    - Dedication address at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library, August 10, 1962.
    - "Fishing Presidents and Candidates," Stanford Review, May - June 1963.
    - Memorandum on history, July 28, 1963.
    - Statement at the Republican National Convention, July 13, 1964.
    - Views on liberty on his 90th birthday, August 10, 1964.
    - "Concerning Honor in Public Life," Reader's Review, n.d.
    - "Free Enterprise in the Social System,", n.d.
    - Letter to the American University Magazine, n.d.
    - Memorandum on the dollar gap
    - Memorandum on Walter Lippmann's proposals
    - Off-the-record comments at the Overseas Press Club, n.d.
    - "School of Business Administration for the Pacific Coast," draft of a letter, n.d.
    - "The Scientists' and Engineers' Promise to American Life," extemporaneous remarks
    - Statement on Cuba, n.d.
    - Compilation of public statements on various selected subjects, with subject index., 1920-1932 (Box 157)
    - Notable quotations and epigrams.
  - Manuscript drafts and galleys of books. (Box 158)
    - Addresses upon the American Road, miscellaneous drafts and galleys., 1948-1950
      - Part I and table of contents.
      - Part II.
      - Part III.
      - Part IV.
      - Part V.
    - An American Epic, vol. I, The Relief of Belgium and Northern France. Drafts and corrected galley proofs. Typescripts, holographs, and printed copies, arranged by date of draft and thereunder by corresponding section in the published version. (Box 159)
      - Draft. Typescript and holograph, unsorted., November - December 1955.
      - Draft, Typescripts and holographs, unsorted., December 1955 - January 1956.
        - Part I.
        - Part II.
        - Part III.
      - "The Third Year." Draft. Typescript and holograph., January 1956.
      - Draft. Typescripts and holographs, unsorted., January - March 1956.
        - Part I.
        - Part II. (Box 160)
        - Part III.
        - Part IV.
        - Part VI.
      - Draft. Typescripts and holographs., April 1956. (Box 161)
        - "First Year."
          - Version A.
          - Version B.
        - "Second Year."
        - "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year."
        - "Fifth Year."
        - "Miscellaneous Subjects."
      - Draft. Typescripts and holographs., August 1956. (Box 162)
        - "Second Year."
        - "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year."
          - Version A.
          - Version B.
        - "Fifth Year."
          - Version A.
          - Version B.
        - "Miscellaneous Subjects."
        - Various chapters, unsorted. (Box 163)
      - Undated. Draft. Typescripts and holographs.
        - "First Year."
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
        - "Second Year."
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
        - "Third Year."
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
          - Part III.
      - Galley A, corrected., September 1956. (Box 164)
        - "First Year."
        - "Second Year."
        - "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year."
        - "Fifth Year."
        - Summary.
        - Miscellaneous.
      - Galley B, corrected., October 1956. (Box 165)
        - Copy 1.
          - Preface and introduction.
          - "First Year."
          - "Second Year."
          - "Third Year."
          - "Fourth Year."
          - "Fifth Year."
        - Copy 2.
          - Preface and introduction.
          - "First Year."
          - "Second Year."
          - "Third Year." (Box 166)
          - "Fourth Year."
          - "Fifth Year."
          - Miscellaneous pages.
      - Galley C, corrected., March 1957.
        - Preface and introduction.
        - "First Year."
        - "Second Year."
        - "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year." (Box 167)
        - "Fifth Year."
        - Miscellaneous pages.
      - Galley C, corrected., June - August 1957.
        - miscellaneous pages., June 1957
        - preface, introduction, and "First Year.", July 1957
        - August 1957.
          - Miscellaneous pages.
          - "Second Year." (Box 168)
          - "Third Year."
            - Chapters 28-39.
            - Miscellaneous chapters.
          - Chapters 52-54.
          - Chapters 55-64.
      - Corrected galley., September 1957.
        - "Second Year" and "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year," "Fifth Year," "Winding Up," and "Notes."
      - Draft and galleys, miscellaneous pages., October 1957.
      - Galley C, corrected with P. Galpin's suggestions., December 1957. (Box 169)
        - "First Year," chapters 1-5.
        - "Second Year" and "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year," "Fifth Year," "Winding Up," and "Notes."
      - Introduction. Typescript and holograph., January 1958.
      - Drafts and galleys, corrected by B. Miller., February 1958.
        - Introduction and "First Year."
        - "Second Year" and "Third Year."
        - "Fourth Year" and "Fifth Year."
      - Miscellaneous drafts and galleys.
    - An American Epic, vol. II, section I, "The Food Administration." (Box 170)
      - Draft, Typescripts and holographs., April 1956.
        - Part I.
        - Part II.
        - Part III.
      - Draft. Typescripts and holographs., May 1956.
        - Part I.
        - Part II.
        - Part III. (Box 171)
        - Part IV.
      - Drafts. Typescripts and holographs., May - June 1956.
      - Draft. Typescripts and holographs., June 1956.
      - Draft. Typescripts and holographs., August 1956.
        - Part I.
        - Part II. (Box 172)
      - Draft. Typescript and holograph., September 1956.
      - Undated. Draft. Typescript.
      - Final draft, n.d.
        - Chapters I - X.
        - Chapters XI - XV.
        - Chapters XVI - XXII.
      - Galley A., November - December 1956.
        - Copy 1.
        - Copy 2. (Box 173)
        - Copy 3, corrected, May 1957.
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
          - Part III.
      - Galley B., May 1957.
        - Copy 1.
        - Copy 2, corrected, July 1957.
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
        - Copy 3, corrected, August 1957. (Box 174)
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
    - An American Epic, vol. II, chapters 21-46, "Relief and Reconstruction."
      - Drafts, Corrected typescripts, arranged to correspond to the published subject matter, thereunder arranged chronologically., 1956.
        - Preface, December.
        - Introduction.
          - October.
          - November.
        - Chapter 27.
          - August.
          - October.
          - November.
          - Undated.
        - Chapter 28.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 29.
          - August.
          - September.
          - October.
          - November.
        - Chapter 30.
          - September.
        - Chapter 31. (Box 175)
          - September.
          - October.
        - Chapter 32.
          - September.
          - October.
        - Chapter 33.
          - September.
          - October.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 34, December.
        - Chapter 35.
          - September.
          - October.
          - December.
        - Chapter 36, n.d.
        - Chapter 37. (Box 176)
          - September.
          - October.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 38.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 39.
          - October.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 40.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 41.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 42.
          - October.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 43.
          - October.
          - December.
        - Chapter 44. (Box 177)
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 45.
          - October.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 46.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Appendix II
        - Miscellaneous drafts.
          - General.
          - "Reconstruction During April,", October 1956.
          - "Reconstruction During May and June,", October 1956.
          - "Reconstruction, July - September,", October 1956.
      - Draft, Typescript., January 1957.
      - Galley, January 1957. (Box 178)
        - Copy 1.
        - Copy 2.
          - Chapters 1-7, corrected.
          - Chapters 8-12, galleys and drafts.
          - Chapter 13, conclusion, galleys and drafts.
    - An American Epic, vol. III. (Box 179)
      - Drafts, Corrected typescripts, arranged to correspond to the published chapters with the same subject matter, thereunder arranged chronologically., 1956.
        - Chapters 1-3.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 4.
          - November
          - December.
        - Chapters 5-6, December.
        - Chapter 8, November.
        - Chapter 9.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 10.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 11, November.
        - Chapter 12, November.
        - Chapter 13, November.
        - Chapter 14.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 15, November.
        - Chapter 16.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 18.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 20, December.
        - Chapter 24, November.
        - Chapters 25-26.
          - November.
          - December.
        - Chapter 35, November.
        - Chapter 37, December. (Box 180)
        - Chapter 38, December.
        - Chapter 39, December.
        - Chapter 40, December.
        - Miscellaneous, December.
      - Drafts, Corrected typescripts, arranged to correspond to the published chapters with the same subject matter, thereunder arranged chronologically., 1957.
        - Introduction.
          - January.
          - February.
        - Chapters 1-3, February.
        - Chapter 5, no month.
        - Chapter 8, February.
        - Chapter 9, February.
        - Chapter 10, no month.
        - Chapter 11, February.
        - Chapter 12, February.
        - Chapter 13.
          - January.
          - February.
        - Chapter 14, no month.
        - Chapter 15, February.
        - Chapter 16.
          - January.
          - February.
        - Chapter 18, February.
        - Chapter 20, no month.
        - Chapter 21, February.
        - Chapter 24, no month.
        - Chapter 25, February.
        - Chapter 26, February.
        - Chapters 27 and 50, August. (Box 181)
        - Chapter 30, August.
        - Chapter 32, no month.
        - Chapter 33, no month.
        - Chapter 41, August.
        - Chapter 47, no month.
        - Chapter 48.
          - February.
          - March.
        - Chapter 55, no month.
        - Chapter 58, August.
        - Chapter 60, August.
        - Chapter 65.
          - February.
          - March.
        - Appendix I, no month.
        - Miscellaneous.
      - Galley 1, "Relief and Reconstruction," corresponds to vol. II, chapters 21-46, and vol. III., 1957
        - Copy 1.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
        - Copy 2. (Box 182)
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
        - Copy 3.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
      - Galley 2, 1957. (Box 183)
        - Copy 1.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
          - Miscellaneous.
        - Copy 2, corrected and revised.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III. (Box 184)
        - Copy 3.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
        - Copy 4, revised. (Box 185)
          - Section I, revised, December 1957.
          - Section II, revised, December 1957.
          - Section III, revised, January 1958.
          - Table of Contents, revised, January 1958.
      - Draft for Galley Z.
        - Section I.
        - Section II. (Box 186)
        - Section III.
      - Galley Z, 1958.
        - Copy 1.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Sections III and IV.
        - Copy 2. (Box 187)
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Sections III and IV.
        - Copy 3.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Sections III and IV.
        - Copy 4. (Box 188)
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
        - Copy 5.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Sections III and IV.
        - Copy 6, revised, March 1958. (Box 189)
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
          - Sections V - VII.
      - Background material
        - Agricultural production.
        - Bibliography.
        - Chronology of, 1919.
        - Commission for Relief in Belgium.
        - Dates.
        - Estonia - ARA. (Box 190)
        - Finland - ARA.
        - Food consumption.
        - Friends Service Committee.
        - Germany - ARA.
        - Greece - ARA.
        - Hoover.
        - Hoover Institution.
        - Imports - Exports.
        - Latvia - ARA.
        - Livestock.
        - Outline.
        - Personnel.
        - Prices.
        - Romania.
        - Shipping.
        - Statistical Tables.
        - Statistical Tables, Revised.
        - Sugar.
    - An American Epic, vol. IV, "Forty-Four Years Fighting Famine and Destitution." Drafts and revised galleys. Typescripts, holographs, and printed matter. Much of this material, particularly Section III, was incorporated into the published form of Vol. IV.
      - Drafts, 1955-1958.
        - Section I.
          - "The American Child Health Association," Typescript., 1955.
          - "Activities on Behalf of American Children" and "The Mississippi Flood," Holograph, typescript, and annotated galley proofs., 1958.
        - Section II, "Relief of the Unemployed," Holograph and typescript., 1958.
        - Section III, "The Second World War and Aftermath," Holograph, typescript, and annotated galley proofs., 1958.
          - Part I.
          - Part II. (Box 191)
          - Part III.
        - Section IV, "The Last Years,", 1958.
      - Draft, Annotated typescript., October 1959.
        - Part I.
        - Part II.
        - Part III.
        - Part IV. (Box 192)
        - Part V.
        - Part VI.
      - Draft, Annotated typescript., November 1959.
        - Draft A.
        - Draft B.
          - Section I.
          - Section II. (Box 193)
          - Section III.
        - Draft C.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
      - Drafts, Annotated typescript., December 1959.
        - Chapters 14-38, annotated typescript.
        - Miscellaneous. (Box 194)
      - Draft, research or source copy. Annotated typescript., November 1960-1961
        - Chapters 1-9.
        - Chapters 10-15.
        - Chapters 16-30.
        - Chapters 31-35.
        - Chapter 37 - trip to Europe, 1947.
        - Miscellaneous chapters.
        - Corrections.
      - Draft, "Hoover draft," basis for March 1962 revision. Annotated typescript., December 1960 - January 1961 (Box 195)
        - Chapters 1-10.
        - Chapters 11-16.
        - Chapters 17-29.
        - Chapters 30-35.
      - Draft, "4A,", March 1962.
        - Section I.
        - Section II. (Box 196)
        - Section III.
        - Section IV.
        - Section V.
      - Draft, "4B,", August - September 1962.
        - Section I.
        - Section II.
        - Section III.
        - Section IV.
        - Section V. (Box 197)
      - Draft, "4C," Annotated typescript., September 21, 1962.
        - Section I.
        - Section II.
        - Section III.
        - Section IV.
        - Section V.
        - Section VI.
      - Draft, "4D," Annotated typescript., December 1962. (Box 198)
        - Section I.
        - Section II.
        - Section III.
        - Section IV.
        - Section V.
      - Draft, "5," Typescript., January 1963. (Box 199)
        - Copy 1. Typescript.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
          - Section IV.
          - Section V.
          - Section VI.
          - Section VII.
          - Section VIII.
        - Copy 2. Typescript (photocopy), annotated.
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
          - Section IV. (Box 200)
          - Section V.
          - Section VI
          - Section VII.
          - Section VIII.
        - Copy 3. Typescript (photocopy).
        - Copy 4. Typescript (photocopy)
      - Draft, February, 1963. (Box 201)
        - Revisions, February 7, 1963.
        - Revisions, February 18, 1963.
        - Revisions, Chapter 16 to Epilogue., February 1963
        - Revised text. Typescript (photocopies).
        - Copy 1.
        - Copy 2. (Box 202)
        - Copy 3.
        - Miscellaneous chapters.
        - Copy 4, "research copy." Annotated and documented typescript (photocopy). (Box 203)
          - Section I.
          - Section II.
          - Section III.
          - Section IV.
          - Section V.
          - Section VI.
          - Section VII.
          - Section VIII.
          - Section IX and Epilogue.
      - Research notes, 1962-1963. (Box 204)
      - Correspondence relating to research, 1963-1964.
      - Galley A.
      - Galley B, corrected.
        - Copy 1.
        - Copy 2. (Box 205)
        - Copy 3.
      - Galley C, corrected.
        - Copy 1.
        - Copy 2. (Box 206)
        - Copy 3.
    - An American Epic, vols. I - IV, miscellaneous drafts.
    - American Individualism, drafts and press clippings, 1923.
    - The Blockade of Germany, edited by Suda Bane and Ralph Lutz, corrected and arranged by Herbert Hoover. (Box 207)
      - Correspondence and memos re manuscript, 1940-1942.
      - Original manuscript. Typescript (carbon copy).
        - Part 1.
        - Part 2.
        - Part 3.
        - Part 4.
        - Part 5. (Box 208)
        - Part 6.
        - Part 7.
        - Part 8.
        - Part 9.
        - Chapter 9. (Box 209)
        - Chapter 9, deletions.
      - Research material, minutes of the meetings of the Supreme Economic Council. Transcript (carbon copy).
        - February - March 1919.
        - April - August 1919.
      - Galley proofs, annotated with Herbert Hoover's corrections, June 1941.
        - Chapter 1.
        - Chapters 2 and 3.
        - Chapter 4, part 1.
        - Chapter 4, part 2.
        - Chapter 5.
        - Chapter 6. (Box 210)
        - Chapter 7.
        - Chapter 8.
        - Chapter 9, part 1.
        - Chapter 9, part 2.
        - Notes on Allied Organizations.
      - Galley proofs, 1941.
        - Copy 1.
          - Part 1.
          - Part 2.
          - Part 3.
          - Deletions from Chapter 9.
          - Additions.
        - Copy 2. (Box 211)
          - Part 1.
          - Part 2.
          - Part 3.
          - Part 4.
          - Part 5.
          - Part 6. (Box 212)
          - Part 7.
          - Part 8.
          - Part 9.
        - Copy 3.
          - Part 1.
          - Part 2.
          - Part 3.
      - Galley proofs, 1942. (Box 213)
        - Revisions.
        - Part I.
        - Part II.
        - Part III.
        - Deletions.
          - Part I.
          - Part II.
        - Documents.
    - Challenge to Liberty, Annotated galley., 1934. (Box 214)
    - Memoirs of Herbert Hoover, Bound galleys.
      - Years of Adventure.
      - Private Citizen, and Secretary of Commerce.
      - The Presidency.
        - Vol. I.
        - Vol. II. (Box 215)
      - Correspondence, 1951-1963.
    - Drafts, miscellaneous, Holographs and typescripts.
  - Reviews of works by Herbert Hoover. (Box 216)
    - Addresses Upon the American Road.
    - An American Epic.
      - Vol. I.
      - Vol. II.
      - Vol. III.
      - Vol. IV.
    - America's First Crusade. (Box 217)
    - The Basis of Lasting Peace.
    - A Boyhood in Iowa.
    - De Re Metallica.
    - Fishing for Fun.
    - Forty Key Questions.
    - Memoirs of Herbert Hoover.
      - Vol. I.
      - Vol. II.
      - Vol. III.
      - Die Memoiren, German translation.
    - The New Day.
    - On Growing Up.
    - The Ordeal of Woodrow Wilson. (Box 218)
    - The Problems of Lasting Peace.
- WRITINGS ABOUT HERBERT HOOVER, 1915-1976 (Box 219-229)
  Articles written by others about Herbert Hoover, arranged in chronological order.
  - "Interesting Westerners," Sunset, June 1915. (Box 219)
  - "Two American Heroes," by William C. Edgar, The Bellman, July 3, 1915.
  - "The Modern Samaritan," Saturday Evening Post, October 21, 1916.
  - "Herbert C. Hoover, A Citizen of the World," by M.R. Parkman, St. Nicholas, May 1917.
  - "America's Food Supply Director," Northwestern Miller, May 2, 1917.
  - "Hoover of Belgium," Saturday Evening Post, May 26, 1917.
  - "Hoover of the C.R.B.," World's Work, June 1917.
  - "Who's Who - and Why," Saturday Evening Post, June 23, 1917.
  - "The Autocrat of the Dinner Table," Saturday Evening Post, June 23, 1917.
  - "What Mr. Hoover Said to Mr. Lloyd George," by Vernon Kellogg, World's Work, July 1917.
  - "Conservation of Food, The Public Service of Herbert C. Hoover," by Honorable James D. Phelan, U.S. Senator, July 16, 1917.
  - "Herbert C. Hoover," by Hugh Gibson, Century, August 1917.
  - "Save and Serve with Hoover," Harris Dickson, Collier's, August 11, 1917.
  - "The Story of Belgium," by J. Gade, Hearst's, September 1917.
  - "Educated Office Boys," by Everett W. Smith, The Stanford Illustrated Review, October 1917.
  - "The Wounded Country That Will Not Die," by J. Gade, Hearst's, October 1917.
  - "Food and the Undergraduate," The Stanford Illustrated Review, November 1917.
  - "Herbert Hoover as Individual and Type," by Vernon Kellogg, Atlantic, March 1918.
  - "The Food Administration," American Institute of Mining Engineers, Monthly Bulletin, August 1918.
  - "Herbert Hoover on Blockade and Bolshevism," n.a., 1919
  - "Herbert Hoover, The Man and the Administration," Congregationalist, March 20, 1919.
  - "The Food Administration, A Test of American Democracy," Historical Outlook, May 1919.
  - "America's Three War Aces," Richmond (Virginia) News-Leader, July 2, 1919.
  - "Herbert Hoover, The Man Who Brought U.S. to World," by Herman Bernstein, McClure's, September 1919.
  - "Sons of the Stanford Red: Hoover - Pioneer," by Dare Stark, Stanford Illustrated Review, December 1919.
  - "If He Were President," Independent, December 13, 1919.
  - "Who Will Be the Next President?", Outlook, December 31, 1919.
  - "Mr. Hoover Looked to as a Symbol," Dearborn Independent, 1920. (Box 220)
  - "Bert, Here Are Your Friends of Stanford," Stanford Illustrated Review, January 1920.
  - "Away with Politics!", Harvey's Weekly, January 1920.
  - "Herbert Hoover as an Educational Illustration," Stanford Illustrated Review, January 1920.
  - "Political Characters to Watch," World's Work, January 1920.